ILGWU Western Massachusetts District Records 5780/120
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Western Massachusetts District Records
1937-1972
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/120
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
The collection contains records of the Western Massachusetts District Council primarily documenting its financial transactions, including records of state and federal tax payments, documentation of investments, fundraising for its Campaign Committee, and benefits paid from the Northeast Department Health and Welfare Fund. A smaller portion of the Western District Council records is correspondence on other matters.
5516686
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Z. Owen, July 20, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The Western Massachusetts District Council began as part of the Northeast Department of the ILGWU. In 1976, the Western Massachusetts District Council became part of the newly-formed New England Region, along with other affiliates in Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Maine, New Hampshire, and Vermont. Within a couple of years, the Western Massachusetts District Council became the Western Massachusetts-Vermont District Council. In 1993, the Western Massachusetts-Vermont District Council merged with the Northern New England District Council (NNEDC); at the time of the ILGWU's merger with ACTWU in 1995, the NNEDC and the Boston Joint Board merged to become the Northern New England-Boston Joint Board District Council.
Jack Albano was the ILGWU representative in the district from the 1940s until 1977. Paul Winslow succeeded him as manager, serving in that role from 1977 to 1984. From 1984 to 1994, Richard Rumelt was regional manager. Following Rumelt, Warren Pepicelli, manager of the Boston Joint Board, led the Northern New England-Boston Joint Board District Council through the ILGWU's merger with ACTWU, and subsequently managed the regional affiliate of UNITE and UNITE-HERE.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains two distinct types of records interwoven through the boxes; administrative documents and correspondence. The administrative paperwork details the daily functions and activities of the Western Massachusetts District Council. There are numerous government documents, such as federal and state tax forms and information reports to the U.S. Department of Labor. Financial transactions are also documented and other monetary matters such as the investments and values for various accounts in Western MA banks. Much information is available for the various health coverage plans, including correspondence and administrative paperwork for the Health Center in Boston; documents for the Staff and Retiree Drug Plans under the ILGWU Health Services Plan; reports of collections and payouts, correspondence, audit reports, and general administration for the Northeast Dept. Health and Welfare Fund; correspondence, reports and transactions for Blue Cross; and correspondence and claims for the Death Benefit Fund.
A second component of the collection consists of correspondence files of individuals including: Mitchell Yager, office manager of the Finance Dept.; Gus Tyler, director of the Education Dept. and administrator of the ILGWU Scholarship Fund; Alfred T. Gustin, controller of the Northeast Dept;, Morris Glushien, general counsel for the ILGWU; Siemon Hamburger, general auditor for the ILGWU; Jack Halpern, field supervisor of the Northeast Dept.; Adolph Held, director of the Welfare and Health Benefits Dept.; Arthur Levine, administrative assistant of the Northeast Dept.; Hugh Maloney, supervisor of the Health and Welfare Fund of the Northeast Dept.; Jack Albano, who held numerous positions, including district manager of Organizing for the Northeast Dept., supervisor for New England and Upstate New York, manager of Local 226, and district manager of the Northeast Dept.; Alexander Bookstaver, controller for the ILGWU; and Louis Brass, general auditor for the ILGWU.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/050: ILGWU Northeast Department Records 5780/055: ILGWU Boston Joint Board Records
Women's clothing industry -- United States.; Women's clothing industry -- Massachusetts.; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Clothing workers --Labor unions -- Massachusetts.; Clothing workers -- United States.; Clothing workers -- Massachusetts.; Industrial relations -- United States.; Industrial relations -- Massachusetts.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. -- Western Massachusetts District.
5516686
- Mark Star: Educational Director, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Taxes Federal [folder 1 of 3], 1938-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Taxes Federal [folder 2 of 3], 1938-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Taxes Federal [folder 2 of 3], 1938-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- U.S. Department of Labor, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- University of Massachusetts, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Mitchell Yager, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Tax: City of Springfield, 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gus Tyler, 1958-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Union Label, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Death Benefit Fund Reports, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Boys' Towns of Italy Scrapbook, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ford, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Four Freedoms Hotel, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Furniture and Equipment Lists, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Alfred Gustin, Controller, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Alfred T. Gustin [folder 1 of 2], 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Alfred T. Gustin [folder 2 of 2], 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Morris P. Glushein, 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Herman Groobert, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Siemon L. Hamburger, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Jack Halpern, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Adolph Held, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Health Center: Boston [folder 1 of 3], 1943-1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Health Center: Boston [folder 2 of 3], 1943-1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Health Center: Boston [folder 3 of 3], 1943-1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Drug Card Correspondence [folder 1 of 2], 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Drug Card Correspondence [folder 2 of 2], 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Insurance, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Western Massachusetts Investments [folder 1 of 2], 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Western Massachusetts Investments [folder 2 of 2], 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Northeast Investment Interest, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Health Services Identification Card Numbers, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Arthur Levine, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- James Lipsig, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Paul Litano, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Harry Lopatin, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Local 75, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Northeast Department H and W Fund Account #1, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Tax: Commonwealth of Massachusetts [folder 1 of 2], 1943-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Tax: Commonwealth of Massachusetts [folder 2 of 2], 1943-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Taxes: State, 1959-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Mark Starr Correspondence, 1941-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Henry M. Clark: Realtor, 1940-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Hugh Maloney, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Massachusetts Department of Labor & Industries, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Massachusetts State Labor Council, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Machine Maintenance, 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous A-L, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- S (misc.), 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous M-Z, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- H and W Fund, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Northeast Department H and W Fund Account #2, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Northeast Department H and W Fund Account #2 [folder 1 of 3], 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Northeast Department H and W Fund Account #2 [folder 2 of 3], 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Northeast Department H and W Fund Account #2 [folder 3 of 3], 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- NCR Machine Reports, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- H and W Audit Reports, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Northeast H and W Administration [folder 1 of 2], 1964-1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Northeast H and W Administration [folder 2 of 2], 1964-1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- ILGWU Dues Schedule, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Affairs, 1961-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- John F. Albano, Supervisor Organizing N.E. and Upstate NY [folder 1 of 3], 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- John F. Albano, Supervisor Organizing N.E. and Upstate NY [folder 2 of 3], 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- John F. Albano, Supervisor Organizing N.E. and Upstate NY [folder 3 of 3], 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Grant, Angoff, Goldman & Manning, 1958-1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Audit Communications, 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Berkshire Coat Factory, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Blue Cross Local Office, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Local Blue Cross Transactions, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Bank Information, 1956-1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Edward Boland, Congressman, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Blue Cross - Blue Shield [folder 1 of 2], 1954-1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Blue Cross - Blue Shield [folder 2 of 2], 1954-1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Alexander Bookstaver, Controller, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Louis Brass [folder 1 of 3], 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Louis Brass [folder 2 of 3], 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Louis Brass [folder 3 of 3], 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Campaign Committee [folder 1 of 2], 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Campaign Committee [folder 2 of 2], 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Campaign Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Campaign Committee, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Lease Information: 69 Stockbridge Street Property, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Census & Survey [folder 1 of 2], 1953-1967 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Census & Survey [folder 2 of 2], 1953-1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Christmas Party Lists and Gifts, 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Constitutional Amendments and Rules, 1953-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Contract Renewal Information, 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Conventions, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Countess York, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Death Benefit Fund [folder 1 of 2], 1959-1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Death Benefit Fund [folder 2 of 2], 1959-1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- District & Executive Council Lists [folder 1 of 2], 1951-1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- District & Executive Council Lists [folder 2 of 2], 1951-1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Donations [folder 1 of 2], 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Donations [folder 2 of 2], 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Wilbur Daniels, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Death Benefit Fund, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Paul W. Deegan, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Disability Membership, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Donations [folder 1 of 2], 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Donations [folder 2 of 2], 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Arnold Dubin, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- David Dubinsky, 1958-1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Evelyn Dubrow, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 19)